<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The exact and true relation of that bloody battell fought betweene His royall Majestie of Swethland, and the Imperial Army the 5 and 6. of November 1632. In the which battell his Majestie was killed. Besides Luelzen, two Germane myles from Leipseich. / Written from Erdfoord by a worthie captaine the 12 of November, who was an eye witnesse to the battell..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12532.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532358</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00110)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2135:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The exact and true relation of that bloody battell fought betweene His royall Majestie of Swethland, and the Imperial Army the 5 and 6. of November 1632. In the which battell his Majestie was killed. Besides Luelzen, two Germane myles from Leipseich. / Written from Erdfoord by a worthie captaine the 12 of November, who was an eye witnesse to the battell..</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wrettoun.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpieces, tailpiece, initial; port. on t.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, creased and torn with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Glasgow. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lützen, Battle of, Lützen, Germany, 1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Campaigns --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden--History--Gustavus II Adolphus, 1611-1632 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EXACT AND TRVE RELATION OF THAT BLOODY BATTELL fought betweene
his Royall Majeſtie of <hi>Swethland,</hi> and the Imperiall Army
<hi>the</hi> 5 <hi>and</hi> 6. <hi>of November</hi> 1632. In the which Battell
his Majeſtie was killed. Beſides <hi>Luelzen,</hi> two Germane myles from
<hi>Leipſeich:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written from <hi>Erdfoord</hi> by a worthie Captaine the 12 of
<hi>November,</hi> who was an eye witneſſe to the Battell.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vos populi, moeſtos leſſus, triſteſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
querelas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi> Cernite; &amp; arcani pectoris acre malum!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, Printed by <hi>Iohn Wreittoun.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:180790:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:180790:2"/>
            <head>THE EXACT AND TRVE RELATION OF THAT BLOODY BATTELL fought
betweene his Royall Majeſtie of <hi>Swethland,</hi> and the Imperiall Army
<hi>the</hi> 5 <hi>and</hi> 6. <hi>of November</hi> 1632. In the which Battell
his Majeſtie was killed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter his Royall Majeſtie of <hi>Swethland</hi> with his Armie
was the 30 day of the laſt moneth of <hi>October</hi> arreard at
<hi>Naumbrugh,</hi> and the enemie being at <hi>Weiſzenfolz,</hi> there was
ſome probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie that he would hold his ſtand: in regard there is a
ſtrong paſſe, and hee lay in his advantage: his Majeſtie preſently
hath a leagure and retrenchments cauſed to be made before <hi>Naumburgh,</hi>
to diſcover and haue a watch full eye v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the further intentions of the
enemie, the which vpon the 4 of November in a manner fled away from
<hi>Weiſzenfolz</hi> after firſt having pillaged Towne and Caſtle: and
turned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe towards <hi>Luelzen</hi> two myles from
<hi>Leipſeich:</hi> wherevpon his Majeſtie preſently vpon the 5. of
November three houres before day, aroſe with his Armie from
<hi>Naumburg,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred yet the ſame day the enemie about two of
the clocke in the afternoone, with playing of his ſmall pieces vpon him; hee
made giue backe, killing ſome of his men, and got a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard <pb facs="tcp:180790:3"/>of the enemies dragoners, on which Fortoun and the Romane Eagle was
painted, which on our ſide was interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a good <hi>omen</hi> and
token, and if we had had yet 2. houres more day, the enemie would haue beene
the moſt part ruined, but night and a thicke miſt befalling vs, wee beganne
to bee quyet on both ſides.</p>
            <p>His Majeſtie continued this whole night in the field,
ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Battalzie intending to purſue and continue this happie
beginning and to fall on vpon the enemie 2. houres before day: but contrarie to
our hopes and expectation, there was againe ſo thicke a fogge that nothing to
the purpoſe could be effected, ſo that his Majeſtie was conſtrained to
ſtay till it was faire day: the miſt being diſperſed by the Sunne. In
the meane while the enemie hath cauſed a trench to be caſt vp vpon the
floate ditch, and expected vs in his advantage. And after his Majeſtie had
cauſed morning prayer to bee ſaid by Doctour <hi>Fabritius,</hi> and the
Sunne by little and little chaſing away the miſt, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likelye to
bee a faire day; his Majeſtie with moſt mooving words exhorted all his
Armies both horſe and foote to fight brauely, and ſaid to the
<hi>Sweds</hi> and <hi>Finnis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My honeſt Brothers behaue your ſelues well this day, and
fight brauely for the Word of GOD, and for your King: in doing this yee ſhall
obtaine grace and mercie with GOD, and honour before all the World: and I my
ſelfe will reward you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourablie; but if yee faile in ſo doing, I
proteſt vnto you that none of your bones ſhall come into</hi> Sweden
<hi>againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Germans his Majeſtie ſaid, <hi>And you my honeſt
Dutch brothers, I beſeech you in generall to behaue your ſelves manfully:
fight brauely with mee, giue no ground, I for my part ſet my life and blood
at the ſtake for your good with you: will you ſtand to mee bravely, without
queſtion it is to bee hoped, GOD Almightie will giue vs the victorie: and you
and your poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will enjoy the fruites thereof. But if you doe not ſo,
then is your Religion and libertie overthrowne.</hi> After which hee ſaid, 
<pb facs="tcp:180790:3"/>
               <hi>Now wee will goe on, GOD Almightie helpe vs all.</hi> And with
that cryed with a lowde voyce to the Heavens, ſaying; <hi>Ieſu, Ieſu,
Ieſu, helpe me this day to fight for the honour of thy Name:</hi> and
advanced in this manner with the whole battell faſting, &amp; went receiving
either meate or drinke vpon the enemie: his Majeſtie leading the Vanguard
himſelfe, and betweene 9. and 10. of the clocke in the forenoone the fight
beganne, and cauſed the enemie at the ſame inſtant time the Towne
<hi>Luelzen</hi> to bee put on fire in two places, becauſe wee might not fall
v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him in that place.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Swediſh</hi> blew and yellow regiment were advanced, and
5. ſhot of great Canon diſcharged vpon the enemie, which had a fine double
advantage of vs, (wee having but the plaine fields) but the float ditch; their
parapet, their muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, their curraſiers, and their Canon, out of
which, hee after our 5. ſhottes diſcharged 80. vpon vs: all which
notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our men did ſo bravely, that they tooke the ditch &amp;
their Trench from them, and betweene and 5. of the clocke 7. Peices of
Artillerie, as alſo diverſe Colours and Cornets, and about all this the
Encounter hath beene ſo fierce on both ſides, that a great many hath beene
ſlaine: after we had reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the the ſaid 7. Peices, the enemie with his
carabats fell vpon our baggage (which was but a few Wagons and Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for
all the reſt were left behind in the Leaguer at <hi>Naum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi>) but were
repulſed with notable loſſe to themſelves, yet withall this our Dutch
cavallerie lighted in ſome diſorder: but juſt at the ſame inſtant a
miſt hapning againe was the cauſe the enemy tooke no notice of this
diſorder: which if hee had perceaved, hee might haue charged vs againe in
ſome other place, and occaſioned greater confuſion; but wee were at
laſt brought in order againe, ſo that in my opinion the miſt did vs more
good than harme: with this the enemy fell with all might and maine vpon vs
againe, and tooke the ſaid 7. Peices from vs againe, and diſperſed ſome
regiments of Cavallerie which <pb facs="tcp:180790:4"/>had given ground; vpon which the
charge was receaved with more earneſtneſſe than ever, and ſome freſh
regiments (the firſt being weake and faint with ſo furious a combat) were
by his Majeſties command brought on, which behaved themſelues ſo
gallantly, that not onely the 7. Peices were recovered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine betweene 2. and
3. of the clocke, but alſo 13. more and all the enemies munition with the
loſſe of a great number of his people, all his Cavallerie, and eſpecially
his Curaſiers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining dead vpon the place and the remainder, except 3.
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments which held themſelves beſide a Windmillne in a ſconce all
began to flie: which made vs imagine the fight had beene at an end and that wee
had abſolutly the victorie, and wee left off ſhooting for halfe an houre,
and all was quyet.</p>
            <p>After this the enemie turned about againe to charge vs and as wee
were afterwards informed by the priſoners, as alſo by the relation in
wryting of our commander at <hi>Hall,</hi> was <hi>Pappin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hame</hi> juſt at
the ſame time with ſundry regiments of freſh folke arryved, which the day
before <hi>Walſten</hi> not thinking that wee would a haue fallen on him, was
gone towards <hi>Hall</hi> to attempt the ſame towne, but vpon this
occaſion in all haſt commanded backe.</p>
            <p>At this arryvall the fugitives did relye themſelves againe and
charged againe with the reſt, where the fight was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued againe vntill
night, with ſuch earneſtneſſe of both ſides that there was nothing
elſe to bee heard or ſeene, but the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Canon, and the haile ſhot
of Muſquet bullets, and this laſt encounter was more hard and furious then
the firſt: yet at the laſt throught the gracious helpe and aſſiſtance
of the higheſt and the Heroicall valour of his excellent Duke
<hi>Bernhard</hi> of <hi>Saxon Weimer,</hi> which at this time his Majeſtie
being dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and deadly wounded in the firſt encounter, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in
chiefe, the victorie is fallen vpon our ſide, and the enemy tooke his flight
toward <hi>Leipſeich</hi> at 9. of the clocke at night with few of his
people, firing his Leaguer, and leaving behind <pb facs="tcp:180790:4"/>ſome of his
baggage, and three Pieces of Artillierie, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede hee tooke along with
him, but was not able to bring them forward, in regard of the darke night wee
were not able to purſue him, and the more, becauſe it was thought he would
ſtand againe the next morning and expect another charge.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a glorious and exceeding great victorie, for the
which wee are not able to render ſufficient thankes to the Almighty GOD: For
on the enemies ſide by the confeſſion of the priſoners, and the view of
the place of the Battell, where dead men lay halfe a mans height one at the top
of another: doth teſtifie is ſlaine and wounded the two third parts of his
Armie among them. <hi>Pappenhem</hi> himſelfe, and moſt of the chiefe
commanders, all their whole artillerie and munitions taken from them, and the
ſmall remainder put to flight.</p>
            <p>Yet in conſideration of the death of our moſt worthie of
glorie, moſt Chriſtian, and in all the world moſt praiſed, and famous,
nothing to bee valved.</p>
            <p>His Majeſtie of moſt high and bleſſed memorie being in the
firſt encounter, was ſhot firſt of all in his Arme, afterwards behind in
his backe, and laſtly with a Piſtoll into his head, and alſo rendred vp
his ſoule as a ſacrifice to the LORD IESVS, and ſpent his Royall blood,
and ventred his life and body with the Proteſtant Electors, Princes, and
States of <hi>Germany,</hi> for the maintenance of your Religion, &amp; the
recoverie of your loſt liberties.</p>
            <p>Off our ſides as farre as I know, is not any great comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
ſlaine but generall Major <hi>Iſler:</hi> yet there are a great many hurt,
amongſt which the Prince <hi>Anhault,</hi> Count <hi>Neils</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell:
<hi>Winchler</hi> Colonell, <hi>Walſtein</hi> and others, but not dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
but how many bee ſlaine of our men, cannot as yet bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly knowne till
wee come to the generall rendevouz: yet the <hi>Swediſh</hi> blew and yellow
regiments of foote, Duke <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds</hi> the Prince of <hi>Anhault,</hi> the
Count <hi>Leuuenſtenis,</hi> and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Brandeſtins</hi> regiment of
Horſe haue ſuffered great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. <pb facs="tcp:180790:5"/>After all this his grace
Duke <hi>Benhard</hi> of <hi>Weimer</hi> being generall over the armie which as
yet conſiſts of 15000. men, retreated himſelfe with his people to
<hi>Weiſzenfolz,</hi> to reſt there a little while, and to expect his
highneſſe the Elector of <hi>Saxon</hi> and Duke <hi>George</hi> of
<hi>Lunenburgh</hi> with their forces, which were not preſent at this
encounter and ſo ioyntly with them to purſuethe victorie.</p>
            <p>The moſt Higheſt grant his grace that all the proteſtaut
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, Princes, and States of <hi>Germanie</hi> may take this
buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to heart, and thankfully acknowledge the deedes and great
faithfulneſſe of the moſt glorious King, and that holie worke begunne for
Religion and libertie, which his royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie of moſt highly
bleſſed memorie hath as it were given them into their hands, and brought to
good termes, maye in time to come with their wontedly hazarding together of
lives, goods, and blood, and through the aſſiſtance of the power of GOD
bee brought to perfection; and that they may expreſſe themſelves
thankfull towards the moſt deſolate, moſt pious, and religious Queene, as
alſo the Crowne of <hi>Swedens</hi> high and inferior officers, which are
reſolved to venter all with them. But if ſo bee (the which God gratiouſly
avert) they ſhould ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate themſelves, and ſuffer themſelves to bee
divided by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther counſells; then might that happen, which the moſt
glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King ſhortly before his death did propheſie: namely, that both
their religion and libertie were overthrowne.</p>
            <p>By this relation I cannot omitt theſe enſuing wordes which his
bleſſed moſt royall Majeſtie manie times, and yet but three dayes
before the battell did ſpeake at <hi>Naumburgh</hi> to Doctor <hi>Fabritius.
Good Maſter Doctor, the buſineſſe ſtandeth well, aad all ſucceedeth
according to our wiſhes, but I feare mee: I feare mee, becauſe that everie
bodie doeth ſo reuerence, and magnifie me, and hold me in a maner for a god,
God wil puniſh me one time or another for that cauſe: yet God knoweth that
I am not pleaſed with it. Now let happen to mee what my moſt loving God
will <pb facs="tcp:180790:5"/>bee pleaſed. Sure I am, that hee will perfect and bring to
an end the buſineſse, becauſe it concerneth the honour of his Name.</hi>
Thus much the King.</p>
            <p>This I thought good in briefe to relate to you, aſmuch as my
ſelfe could learne and informe of, which was my ſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the
beginning to the end of this great capitall bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, (in compariſon of which
the former battell of <hi>Leipſich</hi> is not to bee eſteemed) which
laſted nine whole houres. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the moſt High that hee would bee
pleaſed to aſſiſt my gratious Queene, and all the Counſell and
Officers of the Crowne of <hi>Sweden</hi> with the ſpirit of comfort and
conſolation, that they in a Chriſtian patience may after the loſſe of
ſo great a Treaſure as their King and Lord receive godly comfort in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
wayes.</p>
            <p>Out of all, this is manifeſt to perceive, that not wee, but GOD
Almightie is abſolute maſter of all our willes, lives, thoughts and
ſpirits: and indeed wee may in ſo much the more patience comfort our
ſelves, becauſe our King hath ended his courſe of life in the higheſt
degree of immortall glorie, beeing and remaining before his death, in his
death, and after his death ſtill victorious. His bleſſed Majeſtie his
corps is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Coach with the Armie in perſute of the enemie, till
fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order come at his Queenes arrivall, and the Chancellour
<hi>Oxenſtein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What further will happen I ſhall heereafter let you know: the
royall Chancellerie is conveyed to <hi>Erdfoord,</hi> where they attend the
Chancellors comming.</p>
            <p>This is memorable that his grace Duke <hi>Bernhard</hi> of
<hi>Saxon</hi> when Colonell <hi>Kniphanſen</hi> brought him the poſt of
the Kings (now bleſſed) deceaſe, his grace verie heroically anſwered
then, I deſire to liue no longer, and with that charged the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie with that
courage and Heroicall valour that it is not to bee expreſſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180790:6"/>
            <p>At the cloſing and ſealing vp of theſe, commeth newes that
the enemie hath quyted <hi>Leipſeich</hi> and left a gariſon of two
hundreth men in the Caſtle, taketh his march towards the mountaines
<hi>Zuickaw:</hi> whom Duke <hi>Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard</hi> &amp; the Elector of
<hi>Saxon</hi> his Armie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>And now to conclude this tragicall diſcourſe,</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SHall Woes want words, ſhall ſad ſprung ſighs want
teares?</l>
               <l>Grievd ſoules deepe groanes? ſhall couldie ſobs want
fears?</l>
               <l>Or guſhing griefe lacke ſource? ſhall humane eye</l>
               <l>Reade this diſaſter, and not deſtinie:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay hearts muſt melt, true Chriſtian moanes rebound,</l>
               <l>From tragick tune, a <hi>Mirmidonean</hi> ſound,</l>
               <l>Whilſt thus the angrie fates, O grim deſpight!</l>
               <l>Haue robde ſterne <hi>Europe,</hi> of her great-growne
light:</l>
               <l>That Martiall Prince, <hi>Sweds</hi> North-bred matchleſſe
Starre,</l>
               <l>That thundring Sonne of <hi>Mars,</hi> that life of Warre.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180790:6"/>
               <l>CHRISTS Champion heere on Earth, Religions ſword,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> type, <hi>ADOLPHUS</hi> in aword:</l>
               <l>Whom cruell Death, by three vntymely ſhots</l>
               <l>In fatall field, ſeald vp beſt Souldiers lots:</l>
               <l>O Heavens! let mortall eyes diſſolue in floods,</l>
               <l>Hills, Rockes, and Caves, reſound with eachoing woods</l>
               <l>Our mourning cryes, let whiſtling wyndes tranſport</l>
               <l>Our loues, his praiſe, to Fames eternall Port:</l>
               <l>A Man Monarchick, a conquering Demi-god,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellona's</hi> ſtampe, whoſe hands did weild the Rod</l>
               <l>Of divine Iuſtice, Heavens Mariſhell, and more</l>
               <l>Braue Souldiers Chiftane, Souldiers may deplore,</l>
               <l>And traile their Pikes, come hang their Muſquets downe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe loues haue loſt, the life of true renown.</l>
               <l>For whom that ſoveraigne power, his <hi>Celia</hi> deare,</l>
               <l>May thunder ſighs, and with ſad ſighes ateare:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Swethland</hi> may renew old <hi>Thebes</hi> ſong,</l>
               <l>Like was their griefe, their loſse, their fatall wrong:</l>
               <l>To rouze paſt Warriours worth, time beares record,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Caſtriot</hi> was for valour onely Lord;</l>
               <l>Whoſe bones the <hi>Turkes</hi> reſerue, for a good
ſigne,</l>
               <l>But more <hi>GUSTAVUS,</hi> ſhould bee our deſigne,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Corps, are with his Armie still tranſported,</l>
               <l>Till his grim death bee on his foes retorted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe heart, whoſe hand, whoſe courage, and whoſe
minde</l>
               <l>Had never match, nor after times ſhall finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
